Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice and Campus Ministry Scrapbooks, 1983 - 2004
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice and Campus Ministry Scrapbooks, 1983 - 2004
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice.
6.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
A collection of primarily photographic scrapbooks which depict various Xavier University student activities sponsored by the Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice and Campus Ministry.
XUA-1
History of Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice
Xavier University has demonstrated commitment to its Jesuit and Catholic heritage over the years. In 1981, Benjamin J. Urmston, S.J. proposed through the Vice President for Student Affairs to then Xavier University President Robert Mulligan, S.J., that the University have a department dedicated to faith and justice. He chose the name Peace and Justice Programs. In 1983, at the request of Xavier students, Xavier President Charles Currie designated Dorothy Day House as the home of Peace and Justice Programs and student clubs.
The Division of Religious Development, as the Center for Mission and Identity was originally called, was established by President James E. Hoff, S.J. in March, 1992. Over the years the Center has had several different titles, including the Division of Mission and Ministry and finally, the Center for Mission and Identity in 2009. The Division of Mission and Ministry sponsored Campus Ministry, Peace & Justice Programs and Ignatian Programs.
In these photographic scrapbooks we see the activities that Campus Ministry has provided for students, including prayer and reflection retreats, get-aways, and faith sharing groups. Peace and Justice Programs include activities which raise awareness of social issues as well as sponsor lectures by local, national and international peace and justice specialists. Dorothy Day House is home to a number of student clubs and organizations that are focused on issues of peace and justice, as is reflected by the scrapbook collection.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of primarily photographic scrapbooks covering several Center for Faith and Justice and Campus Ministry sponsored student activities from 1983 to 2004. The albums document Xavier University students taking part in various programs and events, many of which relate to peace and justice issues. Some events include Shantytown, Manresa programs, Appalachian ministry and Ft. Benning protests.
Statement of Arrangement
The collection is arranged in rough chronological order within five boxes.
Restrictions on Access
There are no restrictions on access of these materials.
Acquisition Information
Collection transferred from the Xavier Center for Faith and Justice to the Xavier University Archives on November 15, 2011.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
College students; Student activities
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Dorothy Day Center for Faith and Justice; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Campus Ministry; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Division of Mission and Ministry
Detailed Description of The Collection
This collection consists of scrapbooks and photograph albums covering the Center for Faith and Justice and Campus Ministry's student activities from 1983 to 2004.
- Scrapbook, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Photos of a protest 'Stop the Arms Race, not the Human Race', 1983 - Newspaper Clipping 'Pax Christi presents pastoral letter talks', undated - Photos of National Farm Workers Week, 1986 - Newspaper Clipping of Xavier University (X.U) News-hunger issues, 1984 - Photos of students trip to Appalachia, 1985 - Photos of trip to Rock Castle, Fall 1986 - Photos of Xavier's Urban Experience "An Immersion into the kind of urban life that most of us have never seen" (Students visit RESTOC in Cincinnati's Over-the Rhine neighborhood / hear community members and activists presentations on neighborhood housing perspective / engage in service at an Over-the Rhine homeless man's shelter), possibly 1985 - Newspaper Photo - 'Urban Plunge: X U Students Experience Life of City's Poor', undated - Photo of Protest 'Stop the Arms Race, not the human race', October 1983 - Newspaper Clipping, Xavier News - Community Service of X.U volunteers, 1984 October 18 - More photos from 'reflecting on your experience', 1983 October - Photo, unknown event, possibly 1986 - Student Organizations - Newspaper Clipping X.U News - Peace Week at Xavier March 25th-29th, 1986 March - Photo of 'Alice in Blunderland' Show, undated - Photos of an event (a march?) - Way of the Cross, Pax Christi Xavier, Way of Justice 1986 - Newspaper Photo, solemn march, Good Friday, 1984 April 24 - Newspaper Clipping, Cincinnati Enquirer, 'Peace Marchers', 1986 November 16 - Photos in Washington D.C. -March for Nuclear Disarmament, 1986 November 15 - Ending Hunger event, Food Week flyers, 1985 - X.U Fax, undated - Flyer on Human Rights Week December 2nd - 9th 1985, 1985 December - Photo and written layout of St. Vincent De Paul* 'World Food Day', 1985 October 16 - X.U News Clippings on Student Reflection and Urban Plunge, 1985 - Photos of Nazareth Farm - Spring Break working with poor Appalachians, Sun March 8th through March 14th 1987, 1987 March - Photos of 1st O.C.S.C. (Ohio Community Service Council) Conference, Bellefontaine, OH, 1987February - Newspaper Clippings, Harvest Week, undated - Newspaper Clippings 'The Great Peace March November 19th 1986', 1986
- Scrapbook, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos entitled 'Loyola I', undated - Newspaper Clipping, 1983 - Photos (black and white) of a Campus Ministry event Fall 1989 - The Xavier Players?, 1989 - Photos of an unknown event, 1990 September - Photos of unknown event February 23rd 1990 - Photos of Buddhist Monks visit, possibly 1990 - Photos of event, possibly Christmas, undated - Photos of 'Manresa'* (4-day new student orientation program to reflect on past, present and look to the future), 1989 - Photos of Manresa 1990 - Photos of Costume Party, undated - Roller Skating Photos, undated - Photos of Christmas, 1991 September
- Scrapbook, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Photos of Rural Plunges (students are taken to farms overnight to discuss farming economics and meet with farmers), undated - Adam's County, July 18th-19th, 1986; poem about the Rural Plunge, 1986 - Shelby County, 1986 August - Near Toledo, 1987 June - Urban Experience, 1986 - Photos of Protest Fall 1985 protest 'Stop the Arms Race', 1985- Nicaragua, undated - Photos protesting in Washington, undated - Photos of Rural Plunge ,1987 November - Photos of River Fest, circa 1987-1988 - Photos of St. Vincent de Paul, circa 1987-1988 - Photos of children at Peaslee Neighborhood Center, circa 1987-1988 - Photos of children in Dorothy Day House, circa 1987-1988 - Photos of Hunger Banquet, 1987 - Photos of Urban Experience, 1987 Fall
- Scrapbook, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos, some have a description on the reverse, undated - Photos of unknown events, 1987 - roller skating, Cincinnati zoo, undated - Photos Trick or Treating, 1987 - More unknown events photos, undated - Christmas photos, undated - Halloween Party photos, 1990 - Christmas Party photos, 1990
- Scrapbook, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos ... - Dorothy Day House, undated - Club Day* on the Mall (for students to sign up to clubs), undated - 'Die-In', 1988 Spring - Rural Plunge, ASPI,1988, Spring - D.C. Dive, 1988 Spring - Dorothy Day Medal, 1988 Spring - Urban Experience, 1988 Fall - Harvest Week, 1988, Fall - Hunger Banquet 1988, Fall - Veg-Out, 1988 Fall - Rural Plunge, 1988 - RESTOC (non - profit cooperative in Cincinnati's Over-the -Rhine neighborhood), undated - Amnesty letter writing, undated - Volunteer fair, 1989 - Veg-Out, 1989 Spring - Rural Plunge- Hazard, Kentucky, 1989 Spring - D.C. Dive, 1989 - Dorothy Day Medal, 1989 Spring - Amnesty International, 1989, Spring - Appalachian Work Weekend, 1989, Fall - Amnesty International Freedom Wall, 1989 Winter - "Mock Arrest", Amnesty International 1989 Fall - Unidentified event, 1990 Spring - Volunteer Fair, 1990 January - D.C. Dive, 1990 Spring - Rural Plunge, 1990 Spring - Leadership Awards - Dorothy Day Medal, 1990 April - Katy and Pat's Wedding, 1990 August - Stockholder's meeting at Proctor and Gamble, undated
- Scrapbook, 1983-1998; 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - Peace Week 1983, Pax Christi and Earth Bread (other organizations that supports peace and justice issues) - photo 'stop the arms race not the human race' in Fountain Square, Downtown Cincinnati, 1983 - Hunger Banquet event, undated - Meals at the DDN, 1987 - Washington D.C Clubday on the mall, 1987 - Appalachian work weekend, 1988 - Rural Plunge, 1990 - DD Hawards and friends, 1991 - Shantytown* (students fashion shanty's out of cardboard boxes, wooden crates etc. and experience five days of solidarity with the homeless),1991 November - Rural Plunge, 1990, 1993 - Club Day, 1993 - Food Week, undated - Hunger Banquet, 1993 - Welcome to the Rainforest event, undated - Service in Cincinnati, Life at X.U photos, undated - Dorothy Day House,1994 - Earth Week* (Celebrating Campus sustainability), 1994 - Amnesty, 1994 - Club Day and Shantytown, 1995 - Rothenberg School, undated - Earth Bread's Float, undated - Signing of the Peace Treaty, undated - Photos of 'the service we've done throughout the years' / 'the things we've seen' / 'the places we've been' / 'the people we've worked with' (names on backs of photos) 'people we've met' / Dorothy Day House students' / activities, undated - Earth bread's Christmas party at the Drop-In Center 1995 December - Fundraisers, veg-outs, raising awareness, circa 1997-1998
- Scrapbook, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Scrapbook Contents: Shantytown ,1989 - Sign ins, name, date, time, comments, 1989 - Newspaper clipping :- Xavier Newswire 'Shanty housing available during awareness week, 1989 September 27' - Newspaper clipping: Xavier Newswire 'No place to call their own', 1989 September 13 - Shantytown October 1-4 flyers, 1989 October - Students that took part in shantytown writings on how it felt, undated - Newspaper clippings on Shantytown,1989 October 3 - Photos of 'Shanty's', undated - News Commentary - aired October 3-4 1989, 1989 October - Photos of people in shantytown, in cardboard 'homes', undated - Photos of marching to the capitol, from the Pentagon - Rally X. U student activists 'Housing Now!', undated - Flyer on 'Housing Now!' march on Washington D.C., undated - Housing Assistance Directory, undated
- Scrapbook, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Photos, unknown events, circa 1990-1991 - Photos of Appalachia trip, Beattyville Kentucky - Spring Break 1991, 1991 Spring
- Scrapbook, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Scrapbook Contents: Shantytown 1991 X.U - Names, times and comments, undated - Shantytown flyer - X.U. Earth bread / Pax Christi - September 29 - October 2 1991, 1991 October - Flyer for Documentary showing on reduction in general assistance, 1991 October 1 - Newspaper photo of Shantytown, 1991 October 2 - Newspaper clipping: - Xavier Newswire 'Children: the victims of the crime of homelessness, 1991 September 25 - Newspaper clipping: 'Shantytown positive fundraiser for homeless people', 1991 October 9 - Flyer for Shantytown Sept 29 - Oct 2, 1991 - Flyer - soup line and event speakers, undated - Writing on 'reflection', undated - Photos of Shantytown, undated
- Scrapbook, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Scrapbook Contents: "Homosexuality, Discrimination in the Military, Xavier University, 3800 Victory Parkway, Cincinnati, Ohio 45207" - Newspaper clipping - The Cincinnati Enquirer 'Gays' hopes meet military doubts', 1992 November 15 - Research paper on homosexuals and the law in the military, undated - Newspaper clippings of articles from the Cincinnati Enquirer, 1992 November 25 - Human Rights Ordinance, Front page of Cincinnati Enquirer 'Gay rights ordinance expected to pass', 1992 November 25 - More clippings from Cincinnati Enquirer, undated - Photos of City Hall "The Day of the Vote" - photos of different groups stating who is for and against, undated
- Scrapbook, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Photos of Club Day, 1991 Fall - 'Adopt-a -Family' Certificate of Recognition for Earthcare, undated - Photos of Earth Day, 1992 - Photos of 'Wellness Week' with Earthcare, 1992 Fall - Photos of Recycling, possibly 1991 - Flyer on recycling and Christmas Gift and wrapping ideas from Earthcare, undated - Photos of Rainforest Day, 1993 - Photos of Earth Day ,1991 - Clipping from a Newsletter, 1993 September 17
- Scrapbook, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - Unknown event, undated - Senior Experience(opportunity for graduating seniors to reminisce and celebrate accomplishments / Time to reflect on past and present and look to the future, while finding support in this period of transition in a fun and relaxed environment with friends), 1993 January - Kairos* Retreat (Later known as 'Approach'*. Introductory retreat - introduction to the importance of reflection in one's everyday approach to life and calls students to a greater awareness to God in the world around. Students give talks about their lives and lead their classmates in a similar reflection on their own lives.), 1993 January - Share, 1993 Spring
- Scrapbook, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Scrapbook Contents: Shantytown 1994 - Names, dates / times and comments - The Xavier Newswire clippings on Shantytown, 1994 September 7 - Flyers for 1994 Shantytown, 1994 - Info about homelessness, myths and facts, undated - Flyer for poetry reading, undated - Newspaper clipping from the Cincinnati Enquirer on students spending the night as 'homeless', 1994 September 13 - Information on homelessness in Ohio, undated - Newspaper article from The Cincinnati Post, 1994 October 18
- Scrapbook, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - Unknown event, undated - Kairos Retreat circa 1994-1995 - Appalachian Service Trip, circa 1994-1995 - Lee County Habitat for Humanity - College Friends (Halloween), circa 1994 -1995 - Upward Bound Retreat circa 1994-1995 - Unidentified events, circa 1995-1996 - Manresa, 1995 - Club Day, 1995 - College Friends Halloween Party, 1995
- Scrapbook, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Newspaper Clipping, 'Natural Ties* Retreat marked the greatest number of participants in Xavier's growing club' ('links individuals with disabilities with students of the Xavier community'), 1997 March 19 - Photos of inclusion day, undated - Photos of 'Brad's' house after retreat, undated - Flyer for natural ties follow-up meeting for Xavier students, 1997 April 7 - Flyer for Natural Ties bowling outing, 1997, April 19 - Photos of club day on the mall ,1997 - Flyer for Natural Ties 3rd Annual Wichman family farm picnic - with photos, 1997 September 21 - Photos of natural ties student meeting, undated - Photos of Halloween, 1997 - Flyer for Natural Ties Thanksgiving Pot-Luck Dinner, 1997November 14 - Christmas letter, 1997 November 27 - Flyer and photos of Natural Ties Inclusion Conference, undated - Flyer and photos of Lunch and Movie event, undated - Flyer and photos of Natural Ties March - Xavier University Spring Dance, undated - Flyer and photos of 'Walk the walk' raising money for Children's Hospital Medical Center, undated - Newspaper clipping on Natural Ties - Xavier Newswire, undated
- Scrapbook, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - 'Team' 1997 - 'outside fun', 1997 - 'small groups' (faith sharing groups) - identifications with photos - photos of 'singing / skits', probably 1997 - Koinonia* Retreat (small faith sharing groups), Fall break 1997, 1997 Fall - Clifty Falls, Indiana, probably 1997 - 'Getaway'* and 'Follow-up' (provides 1st year students with an opportunity to escape campus a month after starting college. Focus is to take a step back from busy college life and reflect on what they want to achieve overe the next four years), probably 1997 - Koinonia "Big" Group, circa 1997-1998 - 'Enkounter'* 1998 (the next step after 'approach retreat' in broadening the students spiritual live as and deepening their commitments to faith and justice), 1998 - Kairos, 1997, November - Approach, 1998 - 'Around the office', undated - Spring picnic, 1998 - Senior retreat, undated
- Scrapbook, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - Club day, 1997 - Shantytown ,1997 - Amnesty International trip to Ft. Benning, GA ,1997 - Earth Week ,1998 - DDH organic garden planting, 1998 - Club day, 1998
- Scrapbook, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Scrapbook Contents: - Photos of Shantytown ,1998
- Scrapbook, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Scrapbook Contents: Dedication of the Berkman House honoring Alice Berkman and her family November 6 1998 - Photo of Alice Berkman, probably 1998 - Invitation to members of the Christian Community House of Xavier University and Xavier University Campus Ministry office, probably 1998 - Short reflection ABC House Dedication November 6 1998 - Photo of Alice Berkman, probably 1998 - Photo of girls (with names) in Alice Berkman Christian Community Theme House, 1998-1999 Xavier University, circa 1998-1999 - Photos of Tea Party for Alice, probably 1998 - Photos of friends of Alice and members of Campus Ministry (photographs identified), probably 1998
- Scrapbook, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Scrapbook Contents: Shantytown 1999 - Info on shantytown, 1999 - Some photos and pictures of houses / tents, undated
- Scrapbook, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: - Threshold team retreat, 1999 September 10-11 - Threshold Retreat, 1999 October 7-10 - Dorothy Day House Cookout / Karaoke, 1999 - Club Day, 1999 - Dorothy Day Cookout, 2000 April - Namaste cookout, 2000 April - Threshold photos (participants identified) October 1999 - S.O.A (School of the Americas) protest, 1999 November - Shantytown, 1999
- Scrapbook, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Scrapbook Contents: Campus Ministry, 1999-2000 Photos: - Picnic, undated - Getaway Friday Saturday 22 / 23 October - small groups - names of people in photos - photos of leaders, probably 1999 - Approach, 1999 November - Senior Retreat - barn dance, skits, undated - Farewell Picnic, undated - Seniors 2000, undated - Spring picnic, undated
- Scrapbook, 2000-2002 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Scrapbook Contents: Campus Ministry, 2000-2001 Photos: - Koinonia Leader's Retreat at Milford Spiritual Center's "Kentucky Home", undated - Friday Getaway Retreat, Friday Getaway team - Participants identified, undated - Journey Retreat, 2001, January - Approach, 2001 April - Approach Retreat, 2000 November - Encounter, 2000 - Koinonia Leader's Retreat, 2001 Fall - Senior Retreat, 2001 Campus Ministry 2001-2002 - Get Away retreat for freshmen - (participants identified), 2001 - Get Away's 80's dance team, undated - Approacch, 2001, November - Encounter retreat, 2002 April - Senior Retreat, 2002 - Approach, 2002 April - Threshold at Grailville, 2002 February - Encounter, 2001 November
- Scrapbook, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos: Campus Ministry, 2002 - Koinonia Leader's Retreat, 2002 - Get Away (participants identified), 2002 October 27-29 - Approach, 2002 November - Approach, 2003 December - Journey, 2003 February - Encounter, 2003 February - Koinonia Costume / Bowling party, 2002 October - Approach, 2003 April - Discover, 2003 April - Encounter, 2003 April - Koinonia End of the Year Dinner, 2003 April - Senior class of 2003 Retreat, undated 2003 - 2004 School Year - Campus Ministry Picnic, 2003 - Getaway (participants identified), 2003 September 26-27 - Getaway (participants identified) 2003 September 27-28 - Koinonia Leader's Retreat, 2003 September - Approach Leader's Retreat, 2003 October - Discover Retreat, 2003 October - Encounter Retreat, 2003 November 14-16 - Journey Retreat, 2003 December 6-7
- Scrapbook, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  Scrapbook Contents: Surveys for 4.00pm Liturgy, 2004
- Scrapbook, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photographs of various college student outdoor activities; photos of college students working with children; photos of a trip seemingly in Appalachia, undated
- Scrapbook, Undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  Scrapbook Contents: Halloween Party, undated
- Scrapbook, Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  Scrapbook Contents: Photos of a "Rededication Mass" held at Bellarmine Chapel, undated